Prudence Wayland-Smith Papers
Prudence Wayland-Smith Papers
1925-1994
Wayland-Smith, Prudence;
18 linear feet
Papers of the 20th century social activist, focused on migrant reform, education for migrant children and prison reform. Correspondence, 1925- 1994. Also newspaper clippings, personal notes, and memorabilia including student artwork from migrant schools, photographs and photo boards. Some government documents and publications along with manuscript materials from Wayland-Smith's personal and professional life.
2697344
Biographical History
Prudence Wayland-Smith (1908-1995) was a social activist dedicated to migrant and prison reform for over 50 years.
Born in 1908, Prudence Wayland-Smith was a descendant of the Oneida Community and a member of the Religious Society of Friends (Quakers). She graduated from Curtis High School on Staten Island in 1925 and went on to the Women's College at Brown University.
In 1934 Wayland-Smith was elected president of the Oneida-Kenwood-Sherrill League of Women Voters. Later, she became chairwoman of the Oneida-Kenwood-Sherrill Migrant Committee. Much of the work that the committee carried out was in response to the needs of migrant workers who came up from Florida and other southern states in the summer months to help plant and harvest crops in Oneida County and Madison County in central New York. Migrant families often lived in horrible conditions in labor camps and their children had little or no education. The migrant committee not only worked for better housing conditions and labor rights in migrant camps, they also established day-care centers and summer schools for migrant children so that they could get a basic education. The committee also established a scholarship fund for migrant children going on to college. Prudence remained an active member of the League and the Migrant Committee until the late 1970s when the committee disbanded due to the fact that agriculture had become more mechanized and labor camps were closing.
Beginning in the late 1970s, Wayland-Smith dedicated most of her time to prison reform in local correctional facilities in Oneida and Madison County. As a church leader she brought together other Quaker women to visit inmates, correspond, coordinate Alternatives to Violence workshops, and establish other education programs for prisoners, while also pushing for reform of the treatment of prisoners and conditions within the prisons themselves. Following the Quaker belief that there was goodness in everyone, Wayland-Smith worked to make sure that inmates would have a way to survive once they returned to society. She worked continually in local prisons up until her death at the age of 86 in 1995.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Prudence Wayland-Smith Papers reflect the social reform work that Wayland-Smith carried out from the 1940s to the mid-1990s. The collection is divided into four parts: general files, migrant reform, prison reform and miscellaneous reform.
General files contains material on a variety of non-reform topics, including the Oneida Community Mansion House, Syracuse University, and general news of the day. The majority of the material deals with the Religious Society of Friends (Quakers).
Migrant reform contains correspondence, notes, photos, and other material related to Wayland-Smith's work with regional and state-level migrant committees and organizations, primarily the Oneida-Kenwood-Sherrill Migrant Committee. Included here is information on summer camps for migrant children, the migrant children's scholarship fund, and other related topics. There are also several scrapbooks and other items of memorabilia from the summer camps.
Prison reform materials relate to Wayland-Smith's work assisting prisoners directly as well as her efforts to bring about reforms in the prison system as a whole. This series includes inmate correspondence, news and media coverage, and regional and state-level committee materials as well as material relating to specific prisons in central New York.
Miscellaneous reform covers a range of other areas of reform in which Wayland-Smith was interested, including the peace movement, birth control, human relations, poverty, and non-violence.
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
SCRC has several collections related to prison reform and the Oneida Community. Please refer to the for a complete listing. See in particular
Oneida Community
and
Robert Wayland-Smith Papers
(Prudence's husband).
Separated Material
Some material has been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging, including eight copies of Migratory Labor Notes and four other government publications, a pamphlet on Martin Luther King, Jr. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Activism and social reform; Garofalo, James.; Wayland-Smith, Prudence.; Alternatives to Violence Project.; American Friends Service Committee.; Auburn Correctional Facility.; Auburn Prison Friends Meeting (Auburn, N.Y.); Consumers' League of New York.; Delta Kappa Gamma Society.; League of Women Voters of New York State.; New York State Council of Churches.; New York State Federation of Growers and Processors.; New York State Migrant Child Care Program.; New York (State). Migrant Labor, Interdepartmental Committee on; New York Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends.; Oneida-Kenwood-Sherrill Migrant Committee.; Oneida community.; Quaker Project on Community Conflict of the New York Yearly Meeting.; Quakers -- New York (State); Quakers -- United States -- Political activity.; Society of Friends.; Children of migrant laborers.; Civil rights movement -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Migrant agricultural laborers -- Government policy -- New York (State); Migrant agricultural laborers -- Government policy -- United States.; Migrant agricultural laborers -- Housing -- New York (State); Migrant agricultural laborers -- United States -- 1930-1960.; Migrant agricultural laborers -- United States -- 1960-1970.; Migrant labor -- Camps.; Migrant labor -- Education -- United States.; Prisons -- Law and legislation -- United States.; Race relations.; Annual reports.; Clippings (information artifacts); Negatives (photographic); Photographs.; Slides (photographs); Correspondence.; Essays.; Financial records.; Government records.; Memorabilia.; Newsletters.; Notes.; Scrapbooks.; Serials (publications); Prison reformers -- United States.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Giles, Robert, and Paul Wayland-Smith, 2003.
Inventory
- General files
  - Date book, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Delta Kappa Gamma (Box 1)
  - Government documents (Box 1)
  - Negatives (Box 22)
  - Oneida Community Mansion House (Box 1)
  - Personal, 1920s-1980s; Includes high school papers and continues with later correspondence (Box 1)
  - Religious Society of Friends
    - General (Box 1)
    - Friends Journal
      - 1950s (Box 1)
      - 1960s (Box 1)
      - 1970s-1980s (Box 2)
    - Friends World College (Box 2)
    - Friends World Committee for Consultation (Box 1)
    - Printed material (Box 2)
  - Syracuse University (Box 2)
    - George Arents Research Library (Box 2)
    - Urban Education and Cultural Deprivation, 1964 (Box 2)
  - World and national news (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Migrant reform
  - General correspondence
    - A-G (Box 2)
    - H-Z, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - "Letters from families to whom boxes were sent" Christmas 1957, Winter 1958-59 (Box 3)
    - Migrant letters (Box 3)
  - Government legislation and reform
    - General (Box 3)
    - Congressional hearings and Senate reports (Box 3)
    - Migratory Labor Notes by the President's Committee on Migratory Labor, Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging
    - Printed material (Box 3)
  - Exhibitions on black migration history, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Financial (Box 4)
  - Housing (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
  - Organizations
    - American Friends Service Committee
      See also Prison Reform: Organizations: American Friends Service Committee
      - General (Box 4)
      - 1965-1970 Report (Box 4)
      - Garofalo, James
        - Correspondence (Box 4)
        - 1968 Migrant teachers idea booklet (Box 4)
    - Clinton Migrant Committee (Box 4)
    - Colorado State Department of Education, Report: Providing Education for Migrant Children (Box 4)
    - Consumers League of New York, 1952; includes pamphlet titled Sweatshops In the Sun on the findings of a year's study of migrant farm workers in New York State (Box 5)
    - League of Women Voters
      - Agenda and advocacy (Box 5)
      - Correspondence (Box 5)
      - Finances and fundraising (Box 5)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 5)
      - Publications (Box 5)
      - Reports (Box 5)
    - Mohawk Valley Meeting (Society of Friends) (Box 5)
    - National Migrant Committee and Ministry (Box 5)
    - National Sharecropper's Fund (Box 5)
    - New York State Committee on Farm and Food Processing Labor, annual reports (Box 5)
    - New York State Council of Churches and "Migrant Ministry"
      - General correspondence (Box 5)
      - Financial (Box 5)
      - Meetings (Box 5)
      - Policies, legislation and agenda (Box 6)
      - Projects and reports (Box 6)
      - State Council Reporter publication (Box 6)
      - Training conferences and workshops (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - New York State Federation of Growers and Processors - New York State Migrant Child Care Program
      - General correspondence (Box 6)
      - By-laws and program operations (Box 6)
      - Financial, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Meetings and conferences (Box 7)
      - Newsletters (Box 7)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 7)
      - Summaries and statistics (Box 7)
      - Various local programs (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - New York State Migrant Education Program, 1981 (Box 7)
    - New York State Interdepartmental Committee on Migrant Labor, 1969-1973; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Oneida-Kenwood-Sherrill Migrant Committee
      - Annual reports (Box 7)
      - Correspondence
        - General (Box 8)
        - Committee annual reports (Box 8)
        - George, Anne V., New York State Committee on Farm and Food Processing Labor (Box 8)
        - New York State Education Department (Box 8)
        - Price, Arthur F., New York State Migrant Child Care Program (Box 8)
      - Daily notes of migrant activities (Box 8)
      - Essays/reports on migrant issues and reform (Box 8)
      - Financial, budgets, receipts, fund raising and contributions (Box 8)
      - Journal (Box 8)
      - Lobbying efforts (Box 9)
      - McAllister Summer School/Vernon-Verona-Sherrill Central School (Box 9)
      - Migrant camp choir (Box 9)
      - Migrant labor camps
        - General (Box 9)
        - Photos, migrant labor camps, migrant child-care centers and summer schools (Box 9)
        - Photos, oversize (Oversize 3)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 9)
      - Personal notes (Box 9)
      - The Readers' News (Box 9)
      - Scholarship program
        - Correspondence
          - Brown family general files (Box 9)
          - Brown, Alfred (Box 10)
          - Brown, Anthony (Box 10)
          - Brown, Betty (Box 10)
          - Brown, James (Box 10)
          - Brown, Larry (Box 10)
          - Edwards, Cora (Box 10)
          - Freeman, Mary (Box 10)
          - Holloway, Janie (Box 10)
          - Williams family (Box 11)
        - Funding (Box 11)
        - Memorabilia (Box 11)
        - Memorabilia, oversize (Oversize 3)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
      - Sherrill Child Care Center, part of the New York State Migrant Child Care Program (Box 11)
      - Special Milk Program (Box 11)
      - Workshops/conferences on migrant education (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
    - Oneida-Madison Migrant Committee (Box 11)
    - State-level migrant groups in New York (Box 11)
    - Syracuse Monthly Meeting of Friends (Box 12)
    - Utica Area Migrant Committee (Box 12)
    - World Council of Churches, publication: Migration today: current problems and Christian responsibility (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous conferences, committees, programs and workshops (Box 12)
  - Photographs, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Printed material (Box 12)
  - School memorabilia, 5 folders (Box 13)
  - School memorabilia, oversize (Oversize 3)
  - Scrapbook (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks, oversize (Oversize 2)
  - Slides (Box 23)
  - Slides (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
- Prison reform
  - Advocacy and outreach, coalitions, workshops, projects, legislation (Box 14)
  - General correspondence (Box 14)
  - Inmate correspondence
    - Ford, Glen (Ted), Mid-Orange, Wallkill, Auburn and Elmira correctional facilities; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Johnson, Mel, Auburn Correctional Facility (Box 14)
    - Maloney, Robert (Box 14)
    - Montgomery, Michael, Eastern New York, Mohawk and Auburn correctional facilities; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Moseley, Winston, Auburn Correctional Facility (Box 15)
    - Sims, Bill, Auburn Correctional Facility; See also Prison Reform: Organizations: Auburn Prison Friends (Box 15)
    - Swanson, John, Auburn Correctional Facility (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - News and media coverage (Box 15)
  - Organizations
    - American Friends Service Committee (Box 15)
      See also Migrant Reform: Organizations: American Friends Service Committee
    - Attica Friends Meeting (Box 15)
    - Auburn Correctional Facility
      - General correspondence (Box 15)
      - Auburn Hospitality Association (Box 15)
      - Contraband: Poetry from Prison and Other Ghettos of the Mind (Box 16)
    - Auburn Prison Friends
      - General correspondence, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Correspondence
        - Alternatives to Violence Project (AVP) (Box 16)
        - New York State Department of Correctional Facilities (Box 16)
        - Schmidt, Mattie, mostly financial (Box 16)
      - Auburn International Peace Petition (Box 16)
      - Meeting of Oversight Committee
        - 1975-1982, 5 folders (Box 16)
        - 1983-1994, 9 folders (Box 17)
        - Undated (Box 17)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
    - Central Intelligence Agency (Box 17)
    - Chautauqua County Rural Ministry (Box 17)
    - Church Women United of Oneida (Box 17)
    - Clinton Correctional Facility (Box 17)
    - Department of American Studies, counseling, therapy, and crisis intervention (Box 17)
    - Friends Committee on National Legislation (Box 17)
    - Idyllic Foundation, for troubled young people (Box 17)
    - Land Trust Committee of the New York Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends (Box 17)
    - Madison County Correctional Facility (Box 17)
    - Madison County bail fund, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Mohawk Meeting (Society of Friends) (Box 18)
    - New York State Coalition for Criminal Justice (Box 18)
    - New York State Council of Churches, See also Migrant Reform: Organizations: New York State Council of Churches (Box 18)
    - New York Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends - Alternatives to Violence Project (NYYM/AVP)
      - Correspondence (Box 18)
      - Meetings and minutes (Box 18)
      - Newsletters and reports (Box 18)
      - Policies, by-laws and finance (Box 18)
      - Printed material (Box 18)
      - Prisons Committee (Box 18)
      - Training and workshops (Box 18)
    - Offender Aid and Restoration (OAR) (Box 19)
    - Syracuse Meeting (Society of Friends) (Box 19)
    - Women's Prison Project (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 19)
  - Printed material (Box 19)
  - Training and coursework (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 19)
- Miscellaneous reform
  - Birth control - Planned Parenthood (Box 19)
  - Civil rights movement
    - General correspondence (Box 19)
    - The Fellowship of Reconciliation (Box 19)
    - Magazine clippings (Box 19)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. (Box 19)
    - New York Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends (NYYM), 1968; race relations (Box 19)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 19)
    - Printed material (Box 20)
    - Runnymede Corporation against segregated housing (Box 20)
    - Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) (Box 20)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 20)
  - Discrimination in housing - Housing and Home Finance Agency, Washington DC, 1957 (Box 20)
  - Human relations - National Conference of Christians and Jews (Box 20)
  - Low-income family aid (Box 20)
  - Missions work (Box 20)
  - Peace and community nonviolence
    - General files (Box 20)
    - Quaker Project on Community Conflict (Box 20)
  - Peace movement (Box 20)
    - American Friends Service Committee (Box 20)
      See also Migrant Reform: Organizations: American Friends Service Committee and Prison Reform: Organizations: American Friends Service Committee
    - Disarmament (Box 20)
    - New York Telephone Federal Tax Protest (Box 20)
    - Peacemaker publication (Box 20)
    - Peace walks and vigils (Box 20)
    - Publications and newsletters (Box 21)
    - Vietnam and draft law (Box 21)
    - Women's peace movements (Box 21)
  - Poverty (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 21)